Gökhan Çiflikli Curriculum Vitae

Department of Methodology
London School of Economics and Political Science
Houghton St
London, WC2A 2AE, UK

Phone: +44 7477-104110
Email: g.ciflikli@lse.ac.uk
Website: gokhan.io
GitHub: github.com/ciflikli

Research Interests

I'm a computational social scientist specialising in conflict studies. My ongoing research primarily focuses on predictive models of armed conflict dynamics; exploring the tensions between explanatory versus predictive research; textual analysis of political violence event data; and the circulation and dissemination of social science research.

Professional Experience

Research Appointments

2019-present **Postdoctoral Researcher**. *Automation of the Uppsala Conflict Data Program*. PI Prof. Kristine Eck. Department of Peace and Conflict Research, Uppsala University.

2018-present Postdoctoral Researcher. Quanteda Initiative.

PI Prof. Kenneth Benoit. Department of Methodology, London School of Economics.

2015-2016 **Researcher.** Armed Conflict Database.

International Institute for Strategic Studies, London.

2012-2014 Researcher. Uppsala Conflict Data Program.

Department of Peace and Conflict Research, Uppsala University.

Data and Predictive Modelling Projects

2018-present **Researcher**. *Predictive Analysis for United Nations Peace Operations in Darfur* with John Karlsrud, Allard Duursma, and Luke Abbs.

2018 **Research officer.** *State of the States: Predicting 2018 U.S. Midterm Elections* U.S. Centre, LSE.

2017 **Developer.** *Interactive App for Forecasting Radical-Islamist Terrorism in the U.K.* Alan Turing Institute and the U.K. Cabinet Office.

2017 **Research assistant.** *Visualising Endogenous Modernisation and Post-Communist Support for Democracy* with Prof. Tomila Lankila and Prof. Alexander Libman. LSE.

2016-2018 **Research assistant.** *Geopolitical Slack, Domestic Politics, and Presidents' Use of Force* with Prof. Peter Trubowitz. LSE.

2017-2018 **Research assistant.** *The Hybrid Justice Project* with Prof. Kirsten Ainley. LSE.

2015-2017 **Research assistant.** *Predicting the Escalation of Conflict* with Prof. Nils W. Metternich. University College London.

Gökhan Çiflikli 2

Qualifications

Degrees

2018. Ph.D. International Relations, London School of Economics and Political Science.

Learning Conflict Duration: Insights from Predictive Modelling

Examiners: Prof. Kristin Bakke (UCL) and Prof. Håvard Hegre (Uppsala University)

2017. Visiting Student Researcher Political Science, University of California, Berkeley.

2012. M.SSc. Peace and Conflict Studies, Uppsala University.

2008. B.A. International Relations, Kocaeli University.

Certificates

2017 Introduction to Complexity. Santa Fe Institute.

2016 PGCertHE Associate Level. LSE.

2015 ICPSR Summer Program in Quantitative Methods of Social Research. University of Michigan.

2013 Advanced Quantitative Methods and Research Design. Uppsala University.

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Articles

2018. Phull, Kiran, Gokhan Ciflikli and Gustav Meibauer. 'Gender and bias in the International Relations curriculum: Insights from reading lists'. *European Journal of International Relations*. First Published August 20, 2018.

Works in Progress

Ciflikli, Gokhan. 'Unpacking the Black Box: Local Interpretations of Model-Agnostic Explanations'. To be submitted in 2019 to *Political Analysis*

Ciflikli, Gokhan. 'Learning Conflict Duration: Insights from Predictive Modelling'. To be submitted in 2019 to *Journal of Peace Research*

Ciflikli, Gokhan and Nils Metternich. 'Taking time seriously when evaluating predictions in Binary-Time-Series-Cross-Section-Data'. To be submitted in 2019 to *Political Analysis*

Metternich, Nils, Gokhan Ciflikli, Ali Altaf, and Tatjana Stankovic. 'Predicting the Severity of Civil Wars: An Actor-centric Approach'. To be submitted in 2019 to *Journal of Politics*

Ciflikli, Gokhan, Karsten Donnay, and Nils Metternich. 'Complexity Theories and the Prediction of Conflict Duration'.

Trubowitz, Peter, Gokhan Ciflikli, and Kohei Watanabe. 'Measuring Geopolitical Slack using Automated Newspaper Reporting.' To be submitted in 2019 to *International Studies Quarterly*

Ciflikli, Gokhan and Kristine Eck. 'Improving the Granularity of Event Data using Quantitative Text Analysis'. To be submitted in 2019 to *Journal of Peace Research*

Ciflikli, Gokhan, Gustav Meibauer, and Kiran Phull. 'Social Citation: How Social Trends Influence the Dissemination of Scientific Articles'.

Gökhan Çiflikli

Book Reviews

2017. 'Computational Social Science: Discovery and Prediction', Michael Alvarez (ed.), *Political Studies Review*, Volume 15, Issue 4.

Non Peer-Reviewed Publications

2018-present Blog on predictive modelling, machine learning, and data visualisation for R statistical software at gokhan.io

2018 *A new interactive tool can show us just how polarised Congress has become.* USApp: American Politics and Policy Blog.

2018 Male authors outnumber their female counterparts on international relations course reading lists by more than five to one. LSE Impact of Social Sciences Blog.

2015 Indian government signs a historic peace accord with the Naga insurgents. International Institute for Strategic Studies.

Awards, Scholarships, and Grants

Sir Patrick Gillam Scholarship awarded by the Gillam Fund Committee. LSE. 3,000 GBP. 2017.

University of California, Berkeley Bursary as part of the LSE Ph.D. Mobility Program. 2,300 GBP. 2016.

Michael Leifer Ph.D. Scholarship awarded by the International Relations Department, LSE. 100,000 GBP. 2014-2017.

Collaborator. "Facilitating Data Visualisation and Extraction: A New Interface for the Uppsala Conflict Data Program". 2.4 million SEK (approx. 211,000 GBP). 2014.

Teaching Experience

Postgraduate

Special Topics in Quantitative Analysis: Quantitative Text Analysis. Teaching assistant. *Department of Methodology, LSE*. 2018-2019.

Executive Global MSc in Management Dissertation Supervision. Project officer. *Department of Management, LSE.* 2016-2017.

Undergraduate

Game Theory I. Teaching assistant. Department of Mathematics, LSE. 2016-2017.

Building Democracies from Conflict. Seminar teacher. LSE Summer School. 2016-2018.

Introduction to SPSS and Stats. Lecturer. LSE GROUPS. 2015-2016.

Public Choice and Politics. Teaching assistant. Department of Government, LSE. 2015-2016.

Gökhan Çiflikli 4

Presentations

Conference Papers

2019. ISA 60th Annual Convention.

2018. ISA 59th Annual Convention, PSA Political Methodology Group Annual Conference.

2017. 75th Annual MPSA Conference, ISA 58th Annual Convention, 113th APSA Annual Meeting.

2016. 112th APSA Annual Meeting, Conflict Research Society, ISA 57th Annual Convention.

2015. Conflict Research Society, Peace Science Society (International).

Workshops

2018. Workshop on Forecasting Political Violence. University College London.

2018. ViEWS: A political Violence Early Warning System Workshop. Uppsala University.

Professional Service

Peer-Review

Reviewer for Political Analysis, Conflict Management and Peace Science and Journal of Peace Research.

Memberships

American Political Science Association, Conflict Research Society, International Studies Association, Midwest Political Science Association and Peace Science Society.

Language Skills

Languages: English (fluent), Turkish (native)

Statistical Packages: SPSS, STATA (instructor)

Programming Languages: R (developer), Python

Front-end: HTML, CSS

Database Management: SQL